Okay, let's get started. Okay. Um, so
now let's talk a bit about a recap of
the online RL methods that we've talked
about so far. So, uh, we started with
talking about policy gradients where our
goal was to collect data from our
policy, then increase the likelihood on
actions that led to above average
outcomes. Um so encouraging the policy
to do more of the stuff that led to good
outcomes, less of the stuff that led to
bad outcomes. And then uh we started
introducing this notion of a value
function which can then estimate you we
can use a value function to estimate how
good an action is. Uh and then when we
fit a value function, we can use that to
um then encourage the policy to do more
of what you estimated to be good and
less of what you estimated to be bad. Uh
and we saw a couple algorithms like PO
and SACE that use this sort of actor
critic approach. Um the
we also talked about a few different
ways for fitting value functions and I
want to quickly go through these
different ways again because it's
actually going to be uh play a pretty
important role in today's lecture. So uh
the first thing we talked about is if
you have some state uh in your data and
you want to estimate the value of that
state. One way to do that is to take the
the sum of the rewards over the
trajectory in the future and estimate
the value that way. So the target would
be you'd be trying to fit some vi
of s and your target would be the sum of
rewards from that state onward. So it
would you'd be uh trying to contrast
this with uh
with the sum of rewards
at future time steps uh from future time
steps from t to t. Uh and then your
objective for your value function would
would look something like this where
you're then trying to uh minimize
the this over the states and actions in
your data set.
Um so that was the first simplest way
that we saw to estimate a value
function. And then we saw a way to
potentially get a better estimate
because instead of just summing all the
rewards, you could actually look at your
estimate of the value at an intermediate
state. Um, so say that this is S prime
is your next state right here. Instead
of looking at the sum of rewards from
there, instead you could look at what is
the reward at the next time step plus
the value my estimate for the value at
the next time step and use that as your
target where instead of being the sum of
rewards, the target would be um the
reward at the current time step plus the
value
at the estimated value at the next time
step.
Um, and this is alternative target for
fitting a value function.
And so the full objective would be
Whoops.
The full objective
would be something like this.
and we're trying to
minimize this
over
our data set. We could say our value
function has parameters by
[snorts] we called this kind of
bootstrapping or TD updates, temporal
difference updates. Uh so that was the
second way that we saw for estimating a
value function. Uh and then we also saw
a third way. So um in these two
scenarios the data set um is sampled
from your policy. These were on policy
methods for estimating the value of a
policy.
So these were scenarios where your data
set was sampled from the policy that
you're trying to evaluate.
And we then started to look at a
scenario where what if your data set is
like sampled from some mixture of old
policies.
uh could we use that data in order to
fit a value function?
And to do that um we started looking at
Q functions and
the
um to and with Q functions we can again
use something like bootstrapping where
uh in principle we could use something
like uh q hot pi of fi of s t a t. we're
trying to estimate this and then we
could also use this as our target um
with the caveat that this value function
is going to be for the policy in the
data um and not for the
um the policy that we're trying to learn
and the policy that we're trying to
learn a value function for. And so what
we did instead is we changed our target
to use the Q function.
So we use um we had uh the target as st
plus one a t+1
and
the key difference here was that s and a
and s t+1 are sampled from the data set
but a t+1 is going to be sampled from
the policy that we're trying to learn a
value function for.
Cool. Um, so that's a quick recap of
some of the things that we talked about.
Um, and these are the different ways of
estimating value functions with the key
difference of this last one um, being
something that we can use old policies,
data from old policies for. Um now one
really important aspect of this last one
is that uh we're because we're
bootstrapping and using our own estimate
of the value function at a given state
as the label. Uh we need this Q function
to be trained on actions that that
actually would resemble the actions that
we're going to be evaluating it on. And
so if our policy is very different from
our set of old policies, this label will
not be accurate and then we won't be
able to learn an accurate Q function. So
it needs good coverage over action.
Cool. Um and then those were the
different ways of learning value
functions. The full off policy actor
critic method um looks something like
this where we uh took data from our
policy, stored that in a buffer that had
a number of data from a number of past
policies, sampled some data from that
buffer, uh updated our Q function with
these targets, and then updated our
policy to encourage it to increase the
likelihood on actions that had a high Q
value. And then we can repeat that
process. Okay. Um, so for today, uh,
we're going to be building on some of
those ideas and specifically we're going
to be talking about offline
reinforcement learning. And, uh, in
offline reinforcement learning, we're
trying to learn, uh, from a data set
that was given to us, uh, not collected
by our own policy. Uh, and we'll then
talk about two different methods or two
different classes of methods for doing
offline reinforcement learning. And the
key things that we'll try to see is uh
so I talked about is first the key
challenge that arises in offline RL.
Second uh two different approaches for
offline RL and why they work. Uh and
lastly how offline reinforcement
learning can improve over just imitation
learning which is another way to learn
from offline data sets. The question is
is this Q-learning? Um this is actually
two lectures ago. Uh this is like soft
actor. Um the in Q-learning uh there's
one last change to this. Um so in this
case we're trying to learn Q function
for the policy that we're learning. Uh
the difference that we saw in Q-learning
was we actually trying to learn the Q
function for the optimal policy. And
um
in Q-learning this red marker is not
great. Uh our target was instead um
instead of sampling from the policy that
we're trying to learn a value function
for, we tried to uh pick an action that
was the best action according to that Q
function. And so our target was r of
stat
plus
gamma. And then we were taking a max
over
uh over the next action. So that we were
actually uh
trying to
and the and our goal here was to try to
learn the Q function for the optimal
policy.
And this is also something that can be
done um off policy like without data
from the optimal policy as long as your
estimates have good coverage.
So in offline reinforcement learning
well actually first why offline
reinforcement learning. So um the
process for offline rein for online
reinforcement learning is you collect
data then you update the policy um
either using the latest data or the data
so far
uh and then you repeat that process. Uh
with offline RL, you're actually just
given the data set in advance and then
you want to train a policy on that
provided data set. Um so you're not
actually iteratively collecting data.
Um and there's a number of circumstances
where offline reinforcement learning
might be more useful than online
reinforcement learning. Uh the first is
that you when you're trying to approach
a problem, you might already have a data
set that was collected by an existing
system or by people
and uh collecting data from your current
policy might be risky or might be
unsafe. Uh so for example in uh if
you're trying to learn a policy for
controlling a car to drive on roads uh
you might have a lot of data of people
driving uh that could be very useful for
learning a good policy for driving. Um
and it might be unsafe to actually try
to deploy your policy um especially a
policy that is not very good uh at
driving. [snorts] uh in other
circumstances there um people have
looked at using reinforcement learning
for figuring out good ways to treat uh
people in medical scenarios. Um so for
example uh there was a really cool
project on on um a kind of a seizure
seizure prevention um use case where
you're trying to learn a policy for
figuring out how to prevent seizures. uh
this is a scenario where if you have on
an offline method of of um some existing
system then you could use that to learn
a policy uh without having to collect
data from a policy that uh is not good
in the first place.
Um and then the last point which is
actually a little bit more nuanced is
that [snorts]
uh if you've actually run um online or
multiple times uh you might actually
already have a data set from your
policies and it would be really nice to
reuse that data set uh rather than
trying to recollect data every single
time you try to run an experiment.
If for example you're training a robot
to do something and you want it to like
learn how to grasp something then if you
have a pure online RL method it means
that every single time you need to run
your algorithm you need to recollect
data from your policy. Uh and that can
be pretty inefficient because probably
the first time you run the algorithm
isn't uh you kind of still room for
iteration on the algorithm itself. uh
and generally online data is more
expensive than offline data for that
reason because offline data you can
reuse many times. Also worth noting that
you can blend offline RL and online RL
where you have some existing data set
like in autonomous driving you have a
data set of people driving and then you
want to you train a policy on that and
then you try to improve it with some
online data collection perhaps with a
safety driver um after you have a policy
that's pretty good and uh there's a
number of real world use cases where uh
you will want to blend it because if you
actually are deploying your policy then
it's great to be able to improve it
after you deploy your policy.
Yeah. So the question is can you view
offline RL as a special case of online
but off policy RL um but where you don't
know the data. Uh and in certain in like
that's like definitely one like very
like that's sort of a correct way to
view it. Um one thing that is like a
very strict requirement in offline RL in
like pure offline RL is that you have
have no ability to collect more data. Um
and in that sense it's not really a
special case of online RL because in
online off policy RL uh you can collect
more data. Um that said we'll see that
some of the techniques will um we'll
kind of draw upon like the some of these
off policy techniques from an algorithm
standpoint uh because the in these
scenarios you're using you're able to
use data from old policies. Uh and
that's very useful when you have an
offline data set from some policy that
you don't know. Okay. Um so now let's
talk about this a little bit more
formally. So um say that you um you're
given some data set and the data set uh
maybe has um some trajectories in it. Uh
maybe if it's a driving scenario then
you have some car uh and you have data
sets of people uh driving in a number of
different ways in a number of different
places with a number of different cars.
Uh and
we're going to say that um this kind of
uh constitutes some data set that we're
given.
And
it's helpful to think about kind of
formally think about the policy that
collected this data. Now we don't know
the underlying policy. So for example,
if this was collected by people uh we
don't know what um well first if it's
collected by multiple people then it's
sort of multiple policies and we also
just don't directly have access to that.
Um but it's useful to think about that
policy just from a kind of a
mathematical standpoint. And so we'll
say that uh this data set was collected
by um running some policy that we'll
refer to as the behavior policy or pi
beta. Um
the and if it's collected by multiple
policies then you can think of pi beta
as a mixture of policies. Uh and you can
kind of define that mixture as some like
uh kind of average or or weighted sum
over some constituent policies.
Um so we don't lose any generality by
saying that it's collected by a single
policy.
Um cool. So that's the data set um
sample from some unknown policy.
The it may be a mixture of policies. Uh
if we were to think about the the kind
of distribution over this data, we could
think of it having some underlying state
distribution corresponding to this
policy. Uh an action distribution
dynamics um a reward function.
And then our goal is to learn a good
policy uh that maximizes reward.
And um so ideally we would be able to
take this data set and
be able to uh learn some policy that can
control the car. And ideally uh it's
like maybe a pretty good policy. Maybe
some of the times it does like merge
into another lane. Um but generally we
want a policy uh that we'll refer to as
pi theta and we want to be able to
ultimately maximize
um an objective corresponding to the sum
of rewards for how good this policy is.
And so you can think about that as
maximizing the parameters of this policy
and trying to maximize for uh
trajectories sampled from
uh from this policy maximizing the sum
of rewards
or well
either I guess I'll write it as of our
objective where this is kind of the sum
of rewards for individual states in that
trajectory.
Now, one thing to note here is that uh
this objective is an expectation over
this policy whereas our data was
collected by a different policy. And so
we can think about this as there being
some distribution shift between the
policy that collected the data and the
policy that we're deploying. And we
don't actually get to sample from that
policy. And so that's one of the big
challenges in offline reinforcement
learning.
So there's a kind of this distribution
shift because this expectation is under
the learn policy rather than under the
policy that collected the data. Um and
then it's worth mentioning that the like
the the dynamics of the environment are
going to be constant uh between the data
and the learn policy. So the
distribution shift is only for these uh
trajectories is only uh caused by the
shift in the policy. The question is um
if the data set is comprehensive enough
uh can it turn out that the learn policy
and the behavior policy distribution are
identical. Um
the
generally that's uh extremely rare. Uh
generally that doesn't happen and the
reason is that the
um usually well first um you often want
to improve over your data set and learn
something that's better than the average
driver. Uh and so in that case you're
you might actually end up with a
narrower distribution here than um your
original policy. In the case where your
original policy is very good, then
you're somewhat more in an imitation
learning like setting and you might
still diverge and kind of drift away
from the distribution of um uh in the
data set. Um where does the data come
from? It could be human collected from
some handdesigned system or controller.
Uh it could also be from previous
reinforcement learning runs uh that you
want to reuse. It could be a mixture of
these sources. uh lots of different
places the data could come from.
Okay. Um, now there were some comments
about how this offline reinforcement
learning relates to off-picoly
reinforcement learning. And one natural
question is maybe we could just reuse an
off policy algorithm and uh just run
that off policy algorithm but using uh
the offline data set rather than um
rather than uh recollecting data with
our new policy.
Um does anyone have thoughts on what
will happen if you use an off policy
algorithm like soft actor critic um on
an offline data set?
>> Yeah. So the thought there was that um
we we have this this we're evaluating
our Q estimate on um actions sampled
from our policy and our policy is also
trying to increase likelihood on Q
values on states that have or on actions
that have high Q values and if we have
an offline data set and we're learning a
policy that's different from the d the
policy that collected the data then this
Q estimate that we're supervising we're
using to supervised our Q function may
not be accurate uh because it didn't
actually necessarily see uh actions in
the data that come from the policy we're
learning uh and so we might actually end
up learning an accurate Q function and
if we don't learn an accurate Q function
then we might get a bad policy as a
result and so to walk through that a
little bit more let's say that we um
maybe again have
we could have a little bit of space
here. So um let's say that we have
our um our data set and some of the data
uh here are a few of the actions in the
data like maybe this is A1, this is A2,
this is A3
and um there's other actions that the
car could take that's not in the data
set. So um for example, maybe the car
could go on an adventure over here. Uh
maybe that's A4. Uh, the car could also
like make a U-turn. Uh, that's A5. Uh,
the car could also go backwards. Uh,
maybe that's A6. Uh, so there's all
sorts of actions that the car could do.
And
at the beginning of training, we're
going to be randomly initializing our Q
function. And so if you think about some
like randomly initialized Q function for
a given state,
um maybe it kind of looks kind of like
like somewhat random. Uh
the
for and this is for different actions
then only some of these actions are
present in the data. Uh, and so maybe um
A1, A2, and A3, maybe they're all kind
of within this range.
So this is kind of what's like in
distribution in the data. And then
outside of that, your Q function is
somewhat arbitrary.
And you don't actually see any data for
outside that. Uh and then when you do a
policy update, your policy is going to
say, "Oh, maybe let's let's try to
increase the likelihood on action on
actions that have a high key value. This
is
uh
actions a Q of S comma A. Then what it
will do is it will say okay for this
randomly initialized Q value, maybe
something like this looks good." Uh, and
then if that's outside your data, then
it will um it will still continue to
think that that's a good action because
it'll never actually know what the
proper Q value for that action is.
And so walking through that basically
everything maybe another way to think
about this is that here's your data.
Here are some of the actions that are
out of distribution.
Um, including like A4, A5. It never saw
um a car that for example like makes a
U-turn on the highway. Uh, and so the
key value is randomly initialized for
that. Um, some of those actions that are
out of distribution will arbitrarily
have higher key values, some will have
lower because it's randomly initialized.
and then your policy will exploit those
inaccuracies on the out of distribution
actions.
Um so on the slides uh
we have this term right here.
When you evaluate this Q function on a
prime that's not in the data set. If you
have some randomly initialized Q
function for that state and your data
support only covers part of that then on
the auto distribution actions your Q
function will be unreliable and then
when you do your policy update that's
going to seek out actions where the Q
function is over optimistic.
Uh and then after the policy update,
these key values will be overestimated
because now you're going to keep on
reinforcing that that was good behavior
even when it's not in your data. Um
another perspective on this is that this
is kind of will happen in scenarios
where your learn policy is deviating too
much from your behavior policy. Uh
because these out of distribution
actions, these are things that are very
different from what the behavior policy
did. And if we stayed closer to the
behavior policy then we wouldn't had
have this issue. Uh the question is what
happens if you have a discrete action
space. So um basically everything will
be the same. Uh the you it's possible
that your data set if if in each in all
the states in your data set it has full
coverage of the actions then you won't
have this problem. Uh because everything
will be in distribution. uh but in
practice usually there will be states
where you don't have full coverage of
all actions and you can still see
overestimation in those states. Yeah. So
the question is can you just exclude out
of distribution actions when you're
updating your Q function? Uh yeah and
there are approaches for doing that. Now
the unfortunate thing is we don't
actually know what's in distribution and
out of distribution. So uh we have just
samples of states and actions and for a
given state um you might have one state
that then chooses A1 um then you might
have another state that's not exactly
the same but very similar and that takes
A2 and so in that case um A2 might like
technically
um not be seen for the first state uh
but you don't necessarily know like you
don't know for a given state what's in
distribution and what's out of
distribution. Um and yeah, we'll
basically see basically a key idea
behind offline RL methods is trying
trying to avoid well first trying to
think about how do we deviate not too
much from the behavior policy and second
um can we avoid out of distribution
actions.
Okay. Um so let's talk about mitigating
overestimation. Um this is really the
core goal behind offline methods.
So um
the one approach to offline RL um is
basically to do imitation learning. And
the reason why imitation learning works
is that you're only supervising with
actions that are seen in the data. And
so any sort of approach that uses
imitation learning is going to be
avoiding uh out of distribution actions
uh somewhat implicitly because you're
going only going to be supervising with
actions that are in the data.
Um, now we don't necessarily want to use
vanilla imitation learning because the
offline data may not be optimal. There
might be human drivers in your data set,
for example, that don't drive in the way
that you want your autonomous vehicle to
drive.
And offline uh methods should provide a
way to be better than the policy that
underlies the data by leveraging reward
information.
uh by leveraging the fact that maybe um
you can kind of go through your data set
and say that uh this was a behavior that
was good uh and maybe uh this was a
behavior that was like not as good. Uh
and that reward information can allow
you to get a better policy
and then yeah vanilla imitation learning
can't outperform the the expert or
what's provided in the data.
The other thing that I'll mention is
that um not sure if there's an analogous
situation
there there is actually probably some
analogous situation in driving but um a
good offline method can also stitch
together good behaviors.
So if you have um
where to put this say you have uh
maybe let's put it over here. So say you
have some trajectory in your offline
data set that looks something like this
and another uh trajectory in your data
set that maybe looks something like this
and say that this one got a good reward
at the end and this one got a negative
reward at the end. Then a good offline
method should realize that
um this is a good behavior and also the
first part of this trajectory um if you
continue along the green trajectory at
the end is also uh can be a good
behavior and a good off method should
realize that um that when you're in
these states you should uh essentially
be able to stitch together uh the first
part of this trajectory and the second
part of the green trajectory.
And if you use vanilla imitation
learning, you won't get that kind of
behavior. Instead, what it will do is it
will uh in this state, it will take the
average between these two uh action
distributions.
So what this could look like is if you
have a couple trajectories like this,
then um we know that S1 to S3 is good
behavior. We know um S7 to S9 is good
behavior. And so offline reinforcement
learning methods in principle can
actually learn how to get a policy that
goes from S1 to S9 whereas imitation
learning methods won't be able to do
that.
Okay. Um so before we get into uh
methods that can do that kind of
stitching, let's first talk about like a
very simple baseline method. Uh so
one idea is if you have a offline data
set you could also just take the
trajectories that have high rewards and
only imitate the stuff that is good and
don't imitate the stuff that's bad. Uh
and that seems like a reasonable method.
You have some uh offline data set that
contains a variety of trajectories.
Then what you could do is you could
define a new data set that has only
trajectories that have uh a high reward.
And so what this new data set would look
like is it would be all of the
trajectories in your original data set
except uh conditioned on the reward of
that trajectory being greater than some
threshold. And that threshold could be
uh some percentile of the rewards in
your data set like the 70th percentile
for example like only taking the top 30%
of trajectories.
And then from there you could learn a
policy that maximizes the
likelihood of the actions in this
modified data set. Uh so that would look
like taking the states and actions in
this modified data set and maximizing
the log probability of the actions given
the state. So this is the typical
imitation learning objective.
Cool. Um so this is our uh perhaps our
first offline method. I guess very very
basic uh filter the data set to do the
top k% of data and then imitate the
filtered data set. Um this is a very
primitive approach for using reward
information and it's worth noting that
it's not able to do this kind of
stitching behavior because what it will
do is if this is a like a bad trajectory
it might just filter out that trajectory
entirely and it won't actually learn um
how to take this good behavior and this
good behavior and figure out how to get
from here to here.
Um that said, it's a good baseline. So
if you're going to be trying out any
offline RL method, it's good to try this
first uh and see how well it does and
use that as a benchmark and make sure
that or ideally try to make sure that
your offline method is doing better than
this.
Okay. Now, one of the reasons why I
introduced this is that arguably some of
the best offline RL methods uh are
actually doing something that's not all
that different from this in that they do
have a imitation learning component to
them.
Uh and the idea here is that
the instead of just taking the good
trajectories, we could imitate the data
but weight our imitation learning
objective based on how good the action
was in that transition.
Um now
if you remember uh what we talked about
with regard to value functions and
advantage functions where the advantage
function is how much better is at
compared to what the uh what your policy
does. This advantage function suggests
that if we weighted our imitation
learning objective by the advantage
function then we could get some measure
of how good that action is and get a
policy that is able to learn
effectively.
uh and this will kind of form the
objective of our first offline RL
method. And in particular, what we'll do
is we will
um maximize
uh an objective for a policy that will
be
taking the standard imitation learning
objective but just weighting it by um by
the exponentiated
advantages.
uh and this this will be a sum over
states and actions in our data set. Um
the in terms of the choice to
exponentiate them, there's actually a
way to derive this particular objective.
Um
and I'll mention that on the slides. We
won't go through the derivation. Um but
if you're interested, uh we can see if
we can post it after lecture.
And um in terms of this objective, if we
have a good advantage function and we go
back to the stitching example,
we
for this particular state right here, we
know that the advantage
of this action is is high, right?
Because the value uh the Q value of this
is one. uh the Q value for going this
way uh at least in the data is zero and
the value of this state is um will be
the average of those two outcomes and
[clears throat] so the advantage for
this one will be positive and the
advantage for going this direction will
be negative
and so when we then take our imitation
learning objective and weight it by the
advantages we're going to be telling our
policy that in that state it should go
to the good outcome rather than going to
the bad outcome
And so this objective if you have a good
advantage estimate is capable of kind of
stitching together good behaviors in an
offline data set.
So in terms of the derivation you can
show that this advantage weighted
imitation learning objective is
approximating
um a kale constraint objective uh where
you can show that it's maximizing the um
[clears throat] the the future rewards
as measured by your Q value subject to
the constraint that you're staying close
to your uh behavior policy. Uh, and this
is a a pretty reasonable objective for
offline RL because if you're too far
from your behavior policy, then um you
won't be able to
uh you won't be able to actually uh get
good information about how to improve
your policy.
Okay. So before we talk about how we
estimate the advantage and and what this
advantage will be, any questions on what
this objective looks like?
>> Yeah. So the question is um for this to
like improve over imitation learning, do
we need to assume that our trajectories
have um intersecting states? And the
um the brief answer is that no, we
generally don't have to assume that. And
in this diagram, I actually tried to
have S7 and S3 like not be exactly the
same state. Uh and the reason why we
don't need them to be exactly the same
is that if we're using a neural network
to represent the um the policy and the
advantage function, then it will
naturally um like states and actions
that are very similar to each other will
naturally have similar outputs uh from
that neural network. And so it will be
able to um it should be able to
generalize uh if the states are similar
to each other but not exactly
intersecting. Now uh the degree to this
work how um to how well this works will
depend on like how close those states
are and how large the data set is such
that it can learn a representation that
is um collapsing those representations
to something that looks similar. Uh the
question is in practice do we need to
worry about the exponential term
exploding? Uh when we look at a
practical implementation of this we will
actually add a hyperparameter that
corresponds to the temperature of this.
Um and so the practical algorithm will
have um like a one over alpha times the
advantage and that can help prevent this
from getting extremely large. Uh
yeah and then it I guess it depends a
bit um
there's well we'll talk maybe we'll talk
about also a bit more when we get into
fitting advantages.
Yeah, I I I knew this question would
come up. So, um when we talked about
actor critic methods, uh the objective
looked like kind of similar to this
except instead of exponentiating, we
just had the advantage here. The other
key difference was that here we're
sampling from our offline data set and
in the actor critic objectives um the
action well there's different versions
but we're sampling from an online data
set typically and in the
uh in soft vector critic this action
actually comes from your policy not from
the data set. uh the
there isn't like a very quick way to to
kind of derive where those differences
come from. Um
one [sighs]
I don't want to confuse you but the one
one way uh of thinking about this is
oftentimes offline online objectives
will be optimizing kind of a reverse
kale objective and offline are looking
more at a forward kale objective. But uh
it it's a longer explanation. Yeah.
Okay. Um and there's also some
references here uh as well.
Okay. So we've talked about this
advantage. Now um advantages actually
have some policy associated with them.
Uh it's not um it's the advantage of
taking action A in state S and then
following some policy. Uh and so the
question is uh the first question is
like which policy are we trying to
estimate the advantage for? Uh for now
we can use try to estimate the advantage
of the behavior policy.
Um and then a key question comes up is
how do we want to estimate this
advantage function and ideally in a way
that prevents the overestimation that we
saw before.
Okay. So
the first way that we can estimate the
advantage function uh I mean generally
it will look very similar to what we saw
before when estimating the advantage
function but there's a couple other
considerations.
So
let's say version maybe I'll do this in
a new color. So let's say version one um
oh it's v1
version one we're going to use the
simplest thing that we had before which
is to use Monte Carlo returns. So we can
first fit a value function. Uh
and because we're fitting the value
function for the behavior policy, uh we
don't need to
um it is coming like the data is coming
from the policy that we're trying to
evaluate a value function for. So the
the if we want to fit a value function
with monocolor returns then our
objective looks
uh we're trying to regress to the sum of
future rewards.
So our objective looks something like
this.
So this is something that um basically
supervised learning to the future
rewards. [snorts] Uh and then
once we do this uh which is fairly
straightforward then the question is how
do we get uh the advantage out of this?
There's a couple ways you could do this
uh in the first the first time that we
saw this. The way that we got the
advantage function
for a given state and action was to use
the reward
plus the
value function at the next time step
minus the value function at the current
time step. And these are all the value
function
that we just estimated.
Um, so you could use this uh
the one alternative. Well, so you could
use this. Um, this is going to rely on
having a value function that is fairly
accurate because you're doing this kind
of onestep kind of temporal difference
between um the reward plus the value
here minus the value at the current
state. Uh, and so one alternative thing
that you could do is instead of using um
this
estimated um this reward plus value
which is basically the estimate the
estimated um future rewards if you start
at state T and take action A minus um
your current value is instead you could
simply use the empirical uh sum of
rewards into the future.
And so this could simply be the
um and this is going to be a little bit
simpler uh and
doesn't rely on having a good kind of
temporal difference uh between the two.
And so specifically we can first
estimate the value function by trying to
minimize the difference between our
value estimate and the sum of rewards.
Uh and then to estimate
um the advantage function we can
take the sum of rewards uh for that
trajectory and subtract the value.
in terms of um
this particular um advantage estimate
corresponds to a fairly simple and
fairly popular algorithm called
advantage weighted regression. Uh the
yeah um and
I should emphasize that the the way that
we did it previously where you used R +
V of ST+1 is also valid. Um this simply
corresponds to a method that is used
pretty uh commonly and seems to work
well in practice when you have an
offline data set. Um the question was uh
we talked about before how this is
somewhat high variance and GA is better.
Uh you could also use GE here
definitely. Um this is going to be a
little bit simpler. Uh but the uh yeah
you could also use generalized advantage
estimation here.
>> Yeah that's a good question. So the
question is um are we bringing up this
Monte Carlo because uh when offline data
set we have enough data that sum of
rewards is more accurate and we don't
have the variance issues that we saw
before. Um that's definitely one reason
like when you have a large offline data
set variance is a bit less of a concern.
Um and these are more accurate. Um that
said uh a big part of it is also just
simplicity and uh it's nice there's
yeah it's very nice to have an algorithm
where you're doing kind of supervised
learning to fit the value function and
then you're doing weighted supervised
learning to fit the policy and it's just
a very very simple algorithm. Um next
we'll talk about slightly more
complicated algorithms that um than kind
of this version one right here uh that
can also do a bit better. So it's still
um even when you have an offline data
set there is like variance more variance
in this estimate than uh other estimates
that we'll see in a minute.
Now one question uh that just to like
get your brains thinking a little bit.
So
and the [clears throat] question is what
do you if you did this for a
deterministic data set or a policy that
was deterministic underlying the data
set uh what do you actually learn? And
so as an example, let's say that we have
uh
let's say that we have the car again and
uh maybe the car if it's like um like in
some lanes, maybe it just always goes
straight uh and you never actually see
it like turn left or turn right. uh my
question for you is yeah if you were to
run this algorithm where you are fitting
your advantages uh in this way uh from
the on the data set uh what advantages
will you learn and I'll let you talk
about this for like two minutes and then
we'll come back so talk about this with
your neighbors
okay let's come back does anyone want to
share what you discussed test.
Yeah. So, um what was said is that the
if you're always taking the same action,
then the sum of rewards will be the same
as V. Uh because you don't actually see
any kind of variability in your actions.
And that means that your advantage
estimates will all be zero. Uh and then
taking that one step further, if you
then kind of plug this into this
equation, if all your advantage
estimates are zero, then this
exponentiated term is going to be one.
And then you actually just get back kind
of vanilla imitation learning. Uh and
that's actually um it's kind of nice
that you get that back because uh it
means that for this sort of policy like
you actually can't really do better than
the behavior policy in that scenario
because you don't see any variability in
different actions you can take. Uh and
so this algorithm then uh kind of falls
back on imitation learning in that
scenario. Yeah. Yeah. So the question is
um when collecting data from offline
does this mean that you should kind of
sometimes deviate from the expert policy
just to see more example actions and
yeah generally having uh more diverse
um actions represented in your offline
data set is good for offline RL um
especially if you think that your expert
is not like the optimal thing to do then
you definitely want variability because
then you can actually have a potential
to outperform the expert in your data.
Yeah. Yeah. So the question is like is
it does this happen very often in
practice where your advantages estimates
are zero. Um so the true advantage
function for this policy um is not zero
for other actions. It's just that we
don't see those other actions in the
data. Uh and in practice if you have
variability in the actions then you will
get advantages that are very different
from zero. Uh and so yeah you will
actually see uh a good amount of
variability. It really depends on how
broad your data set is. Yeah. Yeah. So
the question is how do you def how do
you like what would the advance function
do on actions that are not in the data
set. So um in this objective we're
actually only evaluating it on actions
in the data set. Uh and so you don't
have any issues with um with it kind of
going outside the support. Um now if you
did evaluate it on actions outside the
data set uh for a different reason then
it would be uh not accurate. uh it'll
just be whatever um was the result of
like the neural network optimization. If
it's close to the data, it might be
reasonable. If it's far from the data,
it might be like arbitrarily incorrect.
Okay. Um so the full algorithm is we
first fit a value function uh using
Monte Carlo regression and then we trade
a policy where we weight the um we
weight our the the probability of taking
an action or or the likelihood objective
by the exponentiated advantage estimate
where the advantage estimate is given by
um the sum of rewards minus the value
function. uh and we have this
hyperparameter here um that kind of
controls the temperature um or how spiky
this distribution will be.
One of the upsides of this is this
algorithm is very very simple. Uh it's
like yeah the probably the simplest
thing that you can implement that has
the possibility of improving over uh
like filtered imitation learning. Uh it
also avoids querying or training on any
autodistribution actions uh which makes
it more stable. Um that said Monte Carlo
estimation can be noisy uh and we're
learning an advantage estimate for the
behavior policy not for the policy that
we're learning. Uh and so this is going
to be like uh we can only improve so
much over the data set as a result.
Yeah. Yeah. So the question is like um
this is this always close to zero uh and
why not? Uh because you're trying to fit
your value function to the sum of
empirical sum of rewards and then we're
taking the sum of rewards and
subtracting the value from it. Now the
reason why uh if you have a broad data
set that it won't always be zero is that
from an individual state uh you will see
diverse actions and your value function
is going to be maybe say this gets like
+ 10 this gets + one this gets like
minus5 uh your value function for this
estimate is going to be the average of
these numbers so that is three I think
uh
And the sum of rewards for taking this
action is going to be 10. And so then
the sum of rewards minus your value
estimate will be seven. So for this
action
um a is equal to 7. For this one a is
equal to -2 and for this one a is equal
to8.
Um, and so when you have variability uh
from a a state or a state that's very
similar to states in your data set,
that's where you see kind of differences
in outcomes. And that's where your
advantage functions will differ.
Cool. Now, it'd be really nice to be
able to not just use Monte Carlo and be
able to use TD updates or use
bootstrapped updates without having to
query Q on out of distribution actions.
And the issue that we saw with our our
previous objective right here was we
were querying the actions uh quering the
Q function out of distribution actions
right here.
Now one very simple thing that we could
do is instead of querying actions
sampled from the policy that we're
learning, we could just sample a prime
from our data set. Uh and
this is um yeah a very simple
modification and this will prevent this
will make sure that the A prime that
we're seeing is actually always seen in
the data and we will actually have
supervision targets for this S-prime A
prime. Um so this is a very uh simple
modification to this objective and the
um if you estimate the advantage
function in this way or estimate the Q
function and then use that to estimate
your advantage you get an algorithm
called advantage weighted actor critic.
Now note this is this is giving getting
rid of one of the weaknesses of the
original advantage beta regression
algorithm which is that we're able to
use bootstrapping but we're still going
to be estimating the value function for
pi beta and not for the policy that
we're learning. Um so that's still one
downside with this approach.
So from here,
it'd be good to think about if we can
estimate a Q for a policy that's better
than the behavior policy.
And one of the ways to think about this
is that when we're trying to minimize
this bootstrapped objective,
this target right here, this is sort of
like a sample from V of S prime. So like
like we saw here uh V of S prime um it's
not we're estimating kind of the mean
the average of the outcomes the average
of the expected future rewards
uh but there's actually there's kind of
a distribution of outcomes that's
represented in the data
and so if we think about
that distribution
so we have our value function um and if
we thought about the value function for
a given state.
When you are taking different actions,
you see different sums of rewards.
And so there's actually kind of some
underlying distribution
for
kind of in your data for a given state.
So like one state or maybe a bunch of
states see uh a
see a reward that um that that's like at
this value maybe like a smaller number
have a higher sum of rewards in them and
so forth. And then when we do Monte
Carlo regression, if this distribution
like has a mean maybe like right here,
then this is what when we do like when
we're trying to fit like the Monte Carlo
estimate of uh for our behavior policy,
then we get this average right here.
We're kind of averaging over the rewards
that we're seeing.
Now, if we wanted to try to learn a
value function for a policy that's
better than pi beta, we could then like
we could think about maybe instead of
trying to fit the mean of the outcomes
that we see, uh maybe we could try to
fit some other percentile. Uh so this is
like the [clears throat] the um mean.
But maybe if instead we could try to fit
like the 70th percentile or something
like that, then maybe we could actually
get a value function for a policy that
is better than our behavior policy.
So how do we do that? Um
maybe let's go through this on the
slides. So we have when we're trying to
estimate uh rewards plus um future key
functions there's a sample of the values
and if we think about a histogram of the
values for a given state uh when we are
using this target we're using an average
of the of the value the so the L2 loss
right here is giving us that value.
Now the VS for the policy, the best
policy in the support of the data is
going to be right here.
And so maybe there's some way to try to
use a different loss function other than
the L2 loss to get a better policy.
Um, now an idea for how to do this. So
in
when we use an L2 loss uh
we have some like error uh
and so this is like the error plotted on
the x- axis and then L2 loss we have
something like this right where uh maybe
let's call this E this is uh e^2.
And if we instead wanted to get um
if we instead wanted to try to get a
value estimate for this, what we could
do is if we instead of having this kind
of symmetric loss that is is um yeah
symmetric if you're less than zero and
greater than zero, you could instead
use
uh a loss function that looks like this.
And
you could actually show that loss
functions like this will actually um
instead try basically you'll be
penalized less for making errors in a
particular direction. And this will
actually give you a
a value function that looks more like
this. It's actually better than your
behavior policy.
Uh now specifically what this looks like
is if you think about
you have some loss function um we'll
call this uh there'll be some
maybe let's this is respect to error. Uh
this loss function is going to behave
differently if the error is less than
zero versus if the error is greater than
zero. And the
let me just remember what the direction
is. So if it's less than zero so we will
have
and the base case is just x^2 or e e^
squ then we'll have some hyperparameter
that weights our loss by some value and
if lambda is 0.5 then this is the
typical like l2 objective uh because
it'll be e^2 both less than zero and
above zero and if lambda is uh less than
0.5 five then it will be um kind of
downweing the loss when it's greater
than zero and upweing it when it is um
when it's uh sorry downweing it when
it's above zero and uping it when it's
less than zero and um the reverse will
be true when lambda is greater than 0.5
um so what this looks like is instead of
I guess I drew it slightly wrong there
instead of using a loss function it
looks this you can use an asymmetric
loss function uh that is penalizing
errors less in one direction.
Um this is called expectile regression.
Uh it's a kind of a cool trick. Uh if
you you can think about it in terms of
like rather than just um like error or
some arbitrary random variable X uh and
if you define different values of this
lambda term then you get uh these
asymmetric losses that look like this
where if again if lambda is greater
than.5 then you see it as asymmetric in
this direction versus if it's less you
see it asymmetric in the other
direction.
Um and here's kind of another
visualization where if you're trying to
um the the mean of this random variable
uh is shown in the red curve but then
you can get different expectiles uh with
different values of lambda.
So then kind of coming back to our
algorithms, if we want to fit our um
our value function, we can use this
expectile loss uh and
basically fit a value function that is
trying to estimate a value function
that's better than our for a policy
that's better than a behavior policy.
And this will be penalizing you for
overestimating and underestimating, but
it won't be penalizing you as much if
you overestimate a little bit.
Basically, you're off by a little bit.
And this means that when you have uh
these different outcomes and uh these
different kind of outcomes right here,
uh if you get the mean, you get three.
Whereas if you have um I haven't written
down exactly what the the optimum would
be, but for some uh value of lambda, you
might um it'll be optimal instead
instead of outputting the mean, you'll
get it'll be more optimal to output
something like uh like six for example,
where you're penalized less for
for kind of overestimating this value.
Um and yeah, the outcome of the loss
function when you sum things together
will be something that's higher than the
mean.
So in particular for this algorithm,
we'll use the expect loss to fit the
value function. We'll actually also fit
a Q function with the typical mean
squared error loss. Um and we'll
actually use the the value function as
the target. Um so we'll be fitting both
a value function and a Q function. Um
and we'll just be using this expectile
loss for fitting the value function. And
then once we have our Q function and
value function, then we can estimate the
advantage as Q minus V and use the same
kind of uh AWR method to get a policy
where we're waiting the likelihoods by
the exponentiated
uh Q minus V.
Yeah. So the question is will we be
overestimating the value in this case?
So um one thing to note about this
algorithm is we're never going to be um
passing as input actions that are not in
the data uh and that was one of the
major sources of overestimation before.
Now depending on how you set lambda if
you set lambda to be uh like zero then
you will overestimate probably um and
there is a typically you'll choose some
value that's uh kind of maybe 0 2 or 3
something like that's more in the middle
that's not so aggressive. um and you
will be getting an overestimate
of v pi beta. Um and the reason for that
is you're actually trying to estimate
the value of a policy that's better than
pi beta. Uh so you're trying to estimate
um
v pi for um a policy pi that's like
better than pi beta.
So you're kind of purposefully
overestimating uh v pi beta. Um the
question is because we're going to be
gradually improving our policy, would it
make sense to gradually decrease um
lambda? So we're not actually collecting
data from our policy and so uh all the
data is coming from our offline data
set. Uh and in that case the it makes
sense to keep it constant because you
always want to be a fixed amount better
than your behavior policy. Now, if you
did in principle actually do um start
collecting some online data, then it um
then things will change a little bit
because then you'll actually be skewing
your data set to a better policy. Um and
in that case, it actually might make
sense potentially to bring Lambda closer
to zero because or sorry closer to 0.5
uh because you'll then have data from a
better policy, a policy better than your
behavior policy.
So pros of this algorithm, we don't need
to query out of distribution actions.
the policy is still only trained on
actions in the data and we're decoupling
um actor and critic training. So we just
do this uh these critic training. We're
fitting a value function and a Q
function on our data and then once we're
done with that and that's kind of
converged or we've done enough training
then we train our policy.
Cool. Um so this is an algorithm called
implicit Q-learning. Yeah. So the
question is where are we fitting Q? So
we could also use Monte Carlo returns
with this and use the um the expectile
like objective with this term. Um it's
nice to use Q because Q is lower
variance uh than this sum of rewards
right here. Uh and we can fit a Q
function um using kind of the the
bootstrapped backups. Um so all these
ideas are applicable to Monte Carlo as
well. Um but using Q functions like when
you can use this sort of bootstrapped
objective uh which you could only do
with Q functions then you'll get a lower
variance target and then I guess to
summarize kind of the point of offline
RL so online data is really expensive uh
because we have to recollect it every
time we run our algorithm and it's
really really useful to reuse offline
data. Uh, one of the big challenges with
offline RL is this shift between your
behavior policy and your learn policy.
And we talked about a filtered or
weighted imitation learning method as a
baseline. And we talked about how we can
actually explicitly constrain the policy
to the behavior policy by only
supervising the policy on actions in
your data. And so that allowed us to
kind of get rid of uh move away from
this distribution shift problem.
And then this sort of trajectory
stitching idea that we talked about
before allows us to improve over vanilla
imitation learning. Um this example
applications for the algorithm we didn't
cover. Um if you want to train offline
filter behavior coding and implicit
keying are both good approaches. Um but
implicit keying is going to be probably
work better uh if you have um especially
if you have a broader data set. uh and
if you want to do offline pre-training
and online fine-tuning um IQL is
actually a very good algorithm for doing
that. It can also be used uh with online
data collection quite effectively and it
works quite well there. There's also a
variant of IQL called IDQL uh that uses
diffusion policies for your policy class
right here. Um and it also works quite
well. Uh and so if you're interested in
diving more into IQL like algorithms, I
would encourage you to check out IDQL.
It is actually a beyond using diffusion.
It also is a bit different in terms of
how this update is done.